UNIX commands and utilities are distributed with the UNIX system, and there are over 100
to choose from. A command is a UNIX program that's executed in the shell. Commands are
sometimes referred to as tools. For some commands, the shell calls other programs called utilities.
For the user though, there's really no difference between a command and a utility. The table
here shows some examples of UNIX commands. Some of them might be similar to DOS commands
that you're familiar with. Note, though, that the commands are very short and are usually
in lower case. Remember that command names, well, like files and directories, they're
also case sensitive. They must be spelled correctly in the correct case. UNIX commands are usually
very small programs designed to do one simple task. Commands can be combined together in
a shell script, which then becomes a new, more powerful command, and we'll explain some
of these commands in more detail a bit later. Now, the meaning of some of these commands
is pretty self-explanatory. Date shows, well, the date. And some of them are a little bit
more cryptic. AWK represents the initials of the people who created them. Ahu, Weinberger,
and Kernigan, in case you were wondering. The UNIX file system is a hierarchical file
system. There's no concept of record structures. The applications are responsible for defining
the structure of the data that is read or written. A UNIX system can treat a file as
a text file or as a binary file. A text file consists of characters which use a new line
as a separator between lines. A binary file consists of sequences of binary words. File
name extensions are used to identify some common file types used by utility programs.
And there are four file types in UNIX system. There's ordinary disk files, directories,
special files, and first in, first out files. In a UNIX system, every device is associated
with a special file in the slash dev directory. The UNIX kernel uses device drivers to manage
the devices. There's a device driver for each type of device. So, for example, DASD,
tape, terminal, console, printers. Also, main memory can be accessed through a special file
called a pseudo device. Since a device is associated with a file in the file system,
users access a device in the same way as they would just access an ordinary file.
In UNIX, devices are divided into two categories. There's block devices and there are character
devices. Block devices are designed to transfer data at high speeds. So, for example, DASD and tape.
Character devices, also called raw I.O. devices, transfer data in small variable length blocks.
Example of character devices are terminals, printers, and plotters. By the way, TTY stands
for tele typewriter, an electromagnetical typewriter from back in the day.
In a UNIX system, I.O. to a data file and to a device, say, for example, a terminal,
is treated in the same way by using the same system calls. This provides simplicity and
flexibility for the UNIX user. The basic I.O. system calls, those are open, close,
read, and write, do not use I.O. buffering and can therefore be a little bit inefficient
in some situations. There is a portable C library which was designed to provide
portability of programs by using a common I.O. system. Standard I.O., usually abbreviated to
STD I.O., is the name of a library based on the portable C library. Standard I.O. provides a
higher level I.O. interface where the system calls do use I.O. buffering. The buffering,
though, is transparent to the user. Example of standard I.O. functions are F open to open a file
and F printf to write to a file. The big difference between a UNIX system and a ZOS system is that
in UNIX all files are allocated to the kernel. The process that uses the open call to allocate
a file gets file descriptors from the kernel which are used to access the file.
Now, in the next video, we'll continue our look at UNIX functions.